## **CURRICULUM VITAE**

# CRISPUS MICHIRA NYAUNDI P.O BOX 1360-00200, NAIROBI

#### **CONTACT INFORMATION**

Name: Crispus Michira Nyaundi

Cell phone: 0716537530/0753201835

Email: michiracrispus@gmail.com

LinkedIn: Michira Crispus

Skype Id: crispus.nyaundi

#### PERSONAL INFORMATION

Date of Birth: 7<sup>th</sup> March 1993

Id No: 29600155

Passport No: AK0004741

Sex: Male

Marital status: Single

Nationality: Kenyan

Languages: English, Swahili and Ekegusii

#### SUMMARY/CAREER OBJECTIVE

Background in Biotechnology and professional expertise in product quality and safety management systems. More than 6 years of exposure in research laboratory set-up. Experience in carrying out ELISA to test protein product's performance, basic techniques to make products including RNA/DNA isolation, cDNA synthesis, laboratory protocols, quality procedures and analytical instrumentation.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

March 2017- Present: London Distillers (K) Ltd Environmental Health & Safety Officer

**Key roles** 



- ❖ Conducting environmental monitoring and water testing in critical manufacturing & packaging areas.
- ❖ Following safe operating procedures and Material Safety Data Sheet (MSDS) guidance applicable to work performed.
- ❖ Evaluated samples for the presence of objectionable microbial organisms using manual techniques
- ❖ Ensuring use of personal protective equipment and engineering controls (e.g., fume hoods) appropriate to their work.
- Participating in inspections and monitoring programs.
- Ensuring maintenance of quality standards through-out product life cycle to resultant waste generation
- Overseeing safety/quality management systems in the quality control laboratories

#### October 2016- February 2017: National Environment Management Authority

#### **Environmental Health Intern**

- Compilation of field quarterly and annual progress reports
- ❖ Processing of effluent discharge licenses, EIA licenses, and vibration permits for developments and industries
- ❖ Investigating incidents on industrial health and safety such as pollution, accidents at work, noise control, toxic contamination, food poisoning and waste management.
- \* Regular environmental auditing and environmental impact assessments.
- ❖ Analysis of good manufacturing practices and evaluation of product during industrial audits
- Monitoring environmental and health standards according to current industrial regulations and standards

#### April 2016- August 2016: Kenya National Cleaner Production Center (KNCPC)

### Cleaner production and Environmental Sustainability Intern

#### **Key functions:**

- ❖ Analysis of industrial manufacturing processes and product for improvement.
- Ensuring compliance with quality control standards during industrial audits
- ❖ Assessment of overall Product Life Cycles
- ❖ Preparation of reports and documentation required by various regulatory agencies e.g. NEMA and the Pharmacy and Poisons Board.
- \* Review of environmental and quality policies for different industries during audits

#### **Professional Skills acquired**

- ❖ Training in Environmental Impact Assessment and Auditing and expertise through industrial audits and preparation of reports.
- ❖ Working knowledge in Resource Efficient and Cleaner Production in industries
- Quality and Environmental Safety Management Systems

#### Sep 2015- March 2016: Crème Research Limited (Start-Up Research Company)

#### **Operations and Marketing Manager**

#### **Key functions:**

- ❖ Day to day customer queries and marketing through various face-to-face interactions.
- ❖ Maintenance and documentation of reports regarding to projects
- Created PowerPoint presentations for project meetings
- ❖ Performed general office support and administrative tasks as required
- Monitored project tracking systems

#### Nov-Dec 2014: Kenya Agricultural & Livestock Research Organisation (KALRO)

#### **Research Scientist**

#### **Kev functions:**

- ❖ Tissue culture micro-propagation of different indigenous and exotic plants
- ❖ Involved in research on the Maize Lethal Necrosis Virus and Sugarcane Mosaic Virus
- \* Extraction of nucleic acids using different solvents
- ❖ Carried out analytical methods of dissolution, distillation, filtration and gravimetric to ensure a thorough analysis of the samples
- ❖ Assisted in laboratory move across buildings that involved, decontamination of current facilities according to all Bio Safety standards, along with adhering to these in the setup of a new laboratory.
- ❖ Designed and executed ELISA experiments working with both human and mouse IgG in a variety of sandwich assays.
- \* Assisted in verification of proceedings of research activities with the predicted charts
- Performed Phage display experiment, using phage library and panning techniques to determine suitable binding of antibodies.

#### Jan-April 2014: Kridha Limited, Water Treatment Company

- Performed qualitative and quantitative analysis of given samples to deduce the chemical composition, nature and reactive tendencies of the given components
- Developed analytical techniques that reduce time and achieve superior results
- Ensured compliance of the laboratory work with the principles, standards, procedures, and safety measures set by regulatory bodies.
- Prepared necessary solutions, reagents, chemicals and calibration and confirmed the standards
- Interpreted the research findings and draw conclusions, based on research reports

#### Jan-May 2013: St. Anatole Nyanchonori Mixed Secondary School

#### **Teacher and Head of Science Department**

❖ Taught Chemistry Form 3 & 4 and Biology Form 2, 3& 4 classes. I also helped in coaching and mentoring the students in sciences & as assistant Head of sciences Department.

#### Jan-May 2012: Royal Roma Academy Kitale

Helped in coaching and mentoring upper primary pupils.

#### **ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS**

2011-2015: Kenyatta University

Bachelor of Science Biotechnology.

#### 2011(Jan-May): St. Ann's College

Proficiency in computing fundamentals, MS Office applications, use of internet and e-mail in which I attained a Distinction. From this I mastered the ability to work well with computerised equipment.

#### 2007-2010: Maranda High School

**Mean of A- (77 points):** English: A-, Kiswahili: A, Maths: C+, Biology: A, Physics: B, Chemistry: A-, C.R.E: A, Agriculture: A.

#### **Membership to Professional Bodies**

- ❖ Member of the Environmental Institute of Kenya (EIK)
- ❖ National Environmental Management Authority licensed Environment expert (License Expert No.8976)

#### SKILLS AND CORE COMPETENCIES

- Knowledge of chemistry, instrumentation, software applications and statistics required for accurate data interpretation
- Skilled in analytical techniques of sampling, defining, concentrating and preserving samples
- Expertise in handling tools, equipment, and techniques to conduct chemical research
- Excellent report-making and presentation skills that help present complex data in easy-toread format
- Strong time management, task management, and decision making abilities

#### **INTERESTS**

• I enjoy travelling and volunteer activities and volleyball. I also enjoy tennis and was a member of the Maranda High School Tennis Club.

#### **REFERENCES:**

MR. PETER MULI HUMAN RESOURCE MANAGER LONDON DISTILLERS (K) LTD PO BOX 57387-00200 CITY SQUARE. 0722284441 hrm@londondistillers.co.ke

MR.ROBERT ORINA
DEPUTY DIRECTOR FIELD OPERATIONS
NATIONAL ENVIRONMENT MANAGEMENT AUTHORITY (NEMA)
P.O BOX 67839-00200, NAIROBI
0723707601
rorina@nema.go.ke

DR.JANE NYAKANG'O
DIRECTOR
KENYA NATIONAL CLEANER PRODUCTION CENTER (KNCPC)
PO BOX 1360-00200 CITY SQUARE.
0725127461
info@cpkenya.org

DR.REUBEN SOI ASSISTANT HEAD, KENYA AGRICULTURAL RESEARCH INSTITUTE (KALRO) P.O BOX 57811-00200 NAIROBI, KENYA 0727539805

MR.SURESH PATEL
CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER
KRIDHA LIMITED.
P.O BOX 17777-00500, NAIROBI.
(+254)725249249
info@kridha.com